Finding Aid for Peter White Papers 1848-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Peter White Papers 1848-1915
White, Peter, 1830-1908.
Marquette, Michigan businessman, Democratic state senator, and Republican regent of the University of Michigan. Letterbooks and correspondence relating to activities in the Democratic Party in Michigan, particularly in the Upper Peninsula, to his service within the state legislature, and to state and national elections, 1876-1896; also correspondence and other records concerning his extensive business interests that include Northern Michigan iron, insurance, banking, and general investments.
86396 Aa 2; AC
30 linear feet
15 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from the Baker Library, Harvard University (donor no. 1783 ) in 1942. A smaller amount came from the Peter White Library, Marquette, Michigan (donor no. 1970 ) in 1944.
The collection is open for research.
Peter White was born at Rome, New York on October 31, 1830. Around 1838, he moved with his family to Green Bay, Wisconsin. At age fourteen, he left home to seek his fortune first in Mackinac Island, then later in Detroit where he was employed as a clerk in a general merchandising firm. White remained in Detroit for a brief period of time then returned to Mackinac Island, again working as clerk. In 1849, he joined a party headed by Robert J. Graveraet to explore the newly discovered Iron Mountains of Lake Superior. Settling in the region, White became one of the first settlers of Marquette and it was here that he would make his fortune. In 1850, he took charge for the Marquette Iron Company of its general trading store. With the postoffice in the rear of the store, White also served as postmaster for the young community. In 1853, he commenced his banking business establishing the firm of Peter White & Co. This later in 1863 became the First National Bank of Marquette.
In the midst of this activity, White studied and practiced law. In 1856, White and Matthew H. Maynard formed a partnership to sell insurance and practice law. The difficulty which the partners faced in their insurance endeavor was finding insurance companies willing to risk the hazards of insuring a wilderness community like Marquette. In addition to problems associated with fire insurance, marine insurance for the transport of pig iron and iron ore was an essential ingredient in the burgeoning economic growth of the area. White early realized the resource riches of the Marquette area sought to involve himself in every aspect of the iron mining business, not just insurance but also finance, production and marketing.
White also had various political and civic responsibilities. In 1857, he was elected to the state house of representatives as a Democrat from the Upper Peninsula;and in 1875, he was elected to the state senate. Additionally, in 1892-1893, he was a member of the Board of World's Fair Managers for Michigan; also he was a member of the Mackinac Island State Park Commission, and a member of the State Board of Library Commissioners. In 1903, he was elected as a Republican to the board of regents of the University of Michigan. He died June 6, 1908.
The collection documents the development of the economy of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan from the perspective of one of its pioneer entrepreneurs. Through correspondence and other business records, there is documentation of White's extensive business interests in Northern Michigan iron, insurance, and banking. Other portions of the collection concern his service in the state legislature and his involvement in state and national elections, 1876-1896.
Peter White's correspondence, the largest portion of the collection, has been divided into two series: correspondence/business papers and insurance correspondence. The papers for 1850-1853 deal with White's activities as clerk for Robert Graveraet. Also discussed in this early period are legal matters with some material on his work as postmaster and various family matters. The correspondence for 1854-1862 deals with early mining companies with whom he had association and provides some information about the financial aspect of various organizations. White acted as a marketing agent for several companies and this aspect is covered well. The term served by White in the state legislature is covered very sparsely.
Beginning in 1863 White activities expand to encompass insurance and banking concerns. While the iron interest is well represent in the papers for 1863-1873, insurance and banking occupy an increasingly important place. After 1874, White's insurance business is heavily represented in the correspondence. Banking also continues to occupy an important place but the iron companies are far less frequently a subject of discussion. Local politics is also discussed in the correspondence for 1874-1891. As someone who had been actively engaged in politics and public service, White commented on state and national election campaigns from the 1870s to the 1890s. Most notable are letters exchanged pertaining to the campaign of Williams Jennings Bryan in the presidential election of1896. Beginning in 1902, the insurance correspondence decrease and the investment phase of White's career make itself evident. After 1900 correspondence with the University of Michigan and its history department becomes more important.
The remainder of the collection consists of Business Records, divided between folder records and bound records. Each of these series includes records of specific companies with whom Peter White was associated. These include the Phenix Iron Mining Company, the Michigan God Company, the Manhard-Jopling Company, the Lake Superior Leather Company, and the Schoolcraft Iron Company.
Subjects:
American newspapers--Michigan--Lansing.; American newspapers--Michigan--Marquette.; Banks and banking--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Depressions--1873--United States.; Elections--Michigan--1876.; Elections--Michigan--1878.; Elections--Michigan--1880.; Elections--Michigan--1882.; Elections--Michigan--1884.; Elections--Michigan--1886.; Elections--Michigan--1888.; Elections--Michigan--1892.; Elections--Michigan--1896.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Marquette.; General stores--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Insurance--Michigan.; Iron mines and mining--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Ishpeming (Mich.); Land use--Michigan.; Manufactures--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Marquette (Mich.); Marquette County (Mich.); Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan. Mackinac Island State Park Commission.; Michigan Mining School.; Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Northern Michigan College of Education.; Peter White Insurance Agency (Marquette, Mich.); Presque Isle (Marquette, Mich.); Railroads--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); St. Paul's Episcopal Church (Marquette, Mich.); Sault Sainte Marie Canal (Mich.); Shipping--Great Lakes.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); White, Peter, 1830-1908.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
White, Peter, 1830-1908.
Contributors:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Barnes, O. M. (Orlando Mack), 1825-1899.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.; Graveraet, Robert.; Harvey, Charles Thompson, 1829-1912.; Lawton, Charles De Witt, 1835-1909.; McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Smith, Samuel William, 1852-1931.; Thurber, Henry Thomas, 1853-1904.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Winans, Edwin B., 1826-1894.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence/business papers
  - 1848-March 15, 1874, 26 folders (Box 1)
  - March 16, 1874-September 1875, 28 folders (Box 2)
  - October 1875-February 15, 1879, 30 folders (Box 3)
  - February 16, 1879-December 1882, 33 folders (Box 4)
  - January 1883-July 1885, 37 folders (Box 5)
  - August 1885-July 1888, 29 folders (Box 6)
  - August 1888-June 1890, 31 folders (Box 7)
  - July 1890-May 1892, 32 folders (Box 8)
  - June 1892-April 1895, 28 folders (Box 9)
  - May 1895-April 1898, 25 folders (Box 10)
  - May 1898-May 1900, 25 folders (Box 11)
  - June 1900-November 1931, 27 folders (Box 12)
  - January 1902-April 15, 1903, 29 folders (Box 13)
  - April 16, 1903-August 1904, 29 folders (Box 14)
  - September 1904-December 1905, 32 folders (Box 15)
  - January 1906-January 1908, 33 folders (Box 16)
  - February 1908-1915, 8 folders (Box 17)
- Insurance business correspondence
  - Undated January 1884-June 1885, 22 folders (Box 17)
  - July 1885-March 1888, 31 folders (Box 18)
  - April 1888-August 15, 1889, 33 folders (Box 19)
  - August 16, 1889-April 1891, 28 folders (Box 20)
  - May 1891-December 1891, 15 folders (Box 21)
- Business Records (foldered)
  - Iron correspondence July 1884-October 1885, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Financial records 1883 (Box 21)
  - Washington Iron Company annual report 1883 (Box 21)
  - Phenix Iron Company 1887 (Box 21)
  - Legal matters 1889-1890, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Bankruptcy of the Michigan Iron Company 1878, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Pewabic Mining Company case 1890-1899, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Pewabic Mining Company case 1890-1899, 13 folders (Box 22)
  - Michigan Gold Company 1889-1895, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Washington Iron Company 1875-1889 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous subjects 1888-1903, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Sample bills, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Notebook concerning Peter White manuscripts in other repositories (Box 22)
- Business Records (volumes)
  - Various
    - Small account book 1875-1906 (Box 23)
    - Ledger of unknown firm 1869-1872 (Box 23)
    - Private Financial Journal 1868-1878 (Volume 15)
  - Phenix Iron Mining Company
    - Minute book of meetings of the stockholders 1887-1890 (Box 23)
    - Ledger 1887-1890 (Box 23)
    - Ledger 1887-1893 (Box 23)
    - Ledger 1887-1889 (Box 23)
    - Ledger of receipts 1887 (Box 24)
    - Inventory 1887 (Box 24)
    - Record of wages and hours 1887 (Box 24)
    - Reports 1887-1888 (Box 24)
    - Report 1887 (Box 24)
    - Record of stockholders 1880-1896 (Box 24)
    - Record of stockholders 1880-1891 (Volume 3)
    - Record of stock transfers 1880-1881 (Volume 6)
    - Record of stock transfers 1881-1882 (Volume 7)
    - Record of stock transfers 1882-1891 (Volume 8)
  - Michigan Gold Company
    - Ledger 1887-1891 (Box 24)
    - Ledger 1887-1893 (Box 24)
    - Record of stockholders 1887-1892 (Box 24)
    - Minute book 1887-1903 (Box 24)
  - Manhard-Jopling Company
    - Minute book 1893-1897 (Box 24)
    - Ledger 1896-1903 (Box 24)
    - Ledger 1896-1898 (Box 25)
    - Record of stockholders 1893 (Box 25)
    - Ledger 1893-1898 (Box 25)
    - Letterbook 1897-1898 (Box 25)
    - Daybook 1895-1903 (Volume 9)
    - Journal 1895-1902 (Volume 10)
  - A. O. Jopling
    - Letterbook 1885-1896 (Box 25)
    - Letterbook 1896-1901 (Box 25)
  - A. O. Jopling and Company
    - Letterbook 1890-1891 (Box 25)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1861-1863 (Box 26)
    - 1864-1867 (Box 26)
    - 1867-1868 (Box 26)
    - 1872-1873 (Box 26)
    - 1873-1874 (Box 26)
    - 1875-1876 (Box 26)
    - 1877 (Box 26)
    - 1877-1879 (Box 27)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 27)
    - 1881-1888 (Box 27)
    - 1882-1883 (Box 27)
    - 1884-1885 (Box 27)
    - 1885-1886 (Box 27)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 28)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 28)
    - 1889-1900 (Box 28)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 28)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 28)
    - 1904-1906 (Box 28)
    - 1906-1908 (Box 28)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 29)
    - 1903-1905 (Box 29)
    - 1905-1907 (Box 29)
    - 1907-1908 (Box 29)
    - 1900-1902 (Box 29)
  - Lake Superior Leather Company
    - Journal 1866-1875 (Box 29)
    - Ledger 1866-1875 (Box 29)
  - Park Cemetery
    - Ledger 1885-1886 (Box 29)
  - Unknown firms
    - Ledger 1895-1899 (Box 30)
    - Ledger 1902 (Box 30)
    - Ledger of hospital accounts undated (Box 30)
    - Ledger 1899 (Box 30)
    - Ledger 1896-1897 (Box 30)
    - Ledger 1868-1874 (Box 30)
    - Record of lands owned by White undated (Box 30)
    - Ledger 1888-1898 (Box 30)
  - Schoolcraft Iron Company
    - Account book 1867-1870 (Volume 1)
    - Account book 1867-1870 (Volume 2)
  - Unknown firms and miscellaneous
    - Insurance payment ledger 1874-1902 (Volume 4)
    - Ledger 1868-1869 (Volume 5)
    - Record of land business 1875-1883 (Volume 11)
    - Albert A. Foster estate ledger 1899-1903 (Volume 12)
    - Bank Account Record 1900-1902 (Volume 13)
    - Ledger 1896-1898 (Volume 14)
- Photographs
  - Portraits 1890s (Box 30)
Selective Index to Subjects
American newspapers--Michigan.
Papers concerning the Marquette Mining Journal in letter of Alfred P. Swinford, Apr. 20, 1875; also concerning the Lansing Journal in letters, May 5, 1896, of L.E. Rowle and S.L. Smith.
Banks and banking (Upper Peninsula, Mich.).
Papers concerning White's banking interests, 1855-1914, including correspondence with the Michigan Bankers' Association since the 1890's; and papers concerning the iron money dispute, 1868-1875.
Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.
Papers concerning false accusations made in relation to Zachariah Chandler in letters, Mar. 4 and Mar. 6, 1875, with William Brodie.
Depressions--1873--United States.
Papers concerning the panic of 1873, especially letters, Apr. 6, 1874 and Mar. 6, 1878, from Charles N. Fay.
Elections--Michigan--1876.
Papers concerning the election of 1876, especially letters, May 25, Aug. 5 and 7, Sept. 1 and 23, Oct. 20, 26 and 28, and Nov. 21, 1876.
Elections--Michigan--1878.
Papers concerning the election of 1878, particularly the state election and the possibility of White running for the state senate; and letter, Oct. 4, 1878, concerning the influence of mill owners on the vote in Menominee.
Elections--Michigan--1880.
Papers concerning the election of 1880, especially letters, May 15, 1880, concerning the Democratic nominee for President; and other materials, Dec. 1 and 18, 1880, and Jan. 19, 1881.
Elections--Michigan--1882.
Papers concerning the election of 1882, especially letters Oct. 21 and 31, 1882, concerning White as a candidate for the U.S. Congress.
Elections--Michigan--1884.
Papers concerning the election of 1884, especially letter, Sept. 11, 1884, concerning the campaign strategy of the Democratic Party.
Elections--Michigan--1886.
Papers concerning the election of 1886, especially correspondence dealing with patronage; the appointment of Alfred P. Swinford as Governor of Alaska; legislation before the U.S. Legislature in letter, May 25, 1886. of Don M. Dickinson.
Elections--Michigan--1888.
Papers concerning the election of 1888, particularly party patronage; the registration of fraudulent Republican votes in the Upper Peninsula, Aug. 31, 1888; and President Cleveland's tariff message, Dec. 5, 1888.
Elections--Michigan--1892.
Papers concerning the election of 1892, especially letters, Jan. 25 and Apr. 15, 1892, of Don M. Dickinson concerning the Democratic convention; and letter, July 20, 1892, of Daniel J. Campau concerning the Democratic convention.
Elections--Michigan--1896.
Papers concerning the election of 1896, especially letters, Aug.-Nov. 1896, from William G. Mather, Henry Russel, Don M. Dickinson, George H. Barbour, W.R. Coats, Samuel G. Mather, Charles S. Hebard, and the Sparrow and Krell Lumber Co., relating primarily to the opposition to the Bryan ticket.
Episcopal Church--Michigan--Marquette
Papers concerning the affairs of the Marquette Episcopal Church, especially letters, Feb. 18 and Mar. 9, 1879, from Samuel L. Mather; letter, Apr. 24, 1884, from E.R. Bishop; and letters, Oct. 7, 1889 and Dec. 16, 1890, of Wylly Hall.
Episcopal Church--Michigan.
Letters including, Jan. 7, July 14, 1897, Nov. 18, 1886, of George Worthington, March 20, 1886, of Samuel Harris, Feb. 10, 1893, of Bishop Thomas F. Davies, Jan. 30, 1893, of T.H. Robinson, Aug. 26, 1894, July 12, 1895, of G. Mott Williams, dealing with the Michigan diocese of the Episcopal Church.
General stores--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.
Papers concerning White's general store in Marquette, Michigan of the year 1855.
Grand Rapids (Mich.)
Papers concerning inland canal to Grand Rapids, especially letter, May 19, 1888, from E.F. Bailey.
Indians of North America--Michigan.
Papers concerning the obligation of the United States to the Indian, May 16, 1907.
Ishpeming (Mich.)
Papers concerning the politics of Ishpeming in letter, Feb. 16, 1893, of Peter W. Phelps, and letter, June 22, 1895, of William G. Mather concerning city improvements in Ishpeming.
Marquette County (Mich.)
Papers concerning the local politics of Marquette County, especially letters, 1852, Nov. 23 and 25, 1874, and July 21, 1879.
Michigan Mining School.
Papers concerning the development of a mining school in the Upper Peninsula, especially letters, Aug. 3, Sept. 19, and Nov. 21, 1891, and Apr. 9, 1895.
Michigan. Mackinac Island State Park Commission.
Papers concerning the administration of the Mackinac Island Park, especially letters, Dec. 6, 1897, Apr. 27, Nov. 16 and 20, 1898, May 12, 1899, and Jan. 22, 1901.
Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society.
Papers concerning the affairs of the Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society, especially letters, Feb. 28, 1885, July 13, 1886, July 20, 1897, Nov. 28 and Dec. 5, 1888, and Mar. 2, Apr. 11, May 31, and Oct. 31, 1906.
Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.
Papers concerning state and local politics and patronage in the period 1866-1876.
Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1897.
Papers concerning state and local politics and patronage in the period, 1877-1898.
Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.
Papers concerning state and local politics and patronage in the period, 1899-1908.
Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881.
Correspondents include: Lewis Henry Morgan, Aug. 9, 1863; Aug. 1, 1872; July 22, 1874.
Northern Michigan College of Education.
Papers concerning the donation of property to the Normal School in Marquette, especially letters, Feb. 8 and Mar. 1, 1899.
Peter White Insurance Agency (Marquette, Mich.)
Papers concerning the affairs of the Peter White Insurance Agency, 1874-1900.
Presque Isle (Marquette, Mich.)
Papers concerning Presque Isle, Michigan, especially letters, Mar. 16, 1898, from George Haydon and William G. Mather.
Republican Party Mich.).
Papers concerning Republican Party affairs, especially letter, Dec. 5, 1874, concerning the method of the Party in local elections; letter, Dec. 15, 1874, of Edwin J. Hulbert; letter, Dec. 25, 1876, of W.P. Welts.
Sault Sainte Marie Canal.
Papers concerning the celebration of the centennial of the Sault Ste. Marie Canal, especially letters, July 15, 1897; July 9, 1907, of Charles T. Harvey.
Shipping--Great Lakes.
Papers concerning marine insurance on the Great Lakes [throughout]; and letters, Jan., Mar., May 24 and 28, June 1, July 3 and Dec. 16, 1874, concerning the Cleveland Transportation Company owned by the Hannah family.
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Papers concerning the coming of the Civil War, especially letters, 1860, of Ed Hicks; also concerning the personal distress resulting from the war, especially letters, 1869, of Jed Philo Clark Emmons.
World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Papers concerning the Chicago Worlds Fair of 1893, especially letters, Feb. 8 and 27, Apr. 5, 11, and 12, Aug. 2, Nov. 13 and 16, Dec. 8, 12-13, 1893, and Feb. 23-24, 1894.
Selective index to correspondents
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.
Jan. 31, 1895
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
July 3, 1893-May 26, 1908
Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.
Oct. 31, 1889 and Dec. 30, 1889
Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.
Feb. 26, 1906-Apr. 7, 1908
Barnes, O. M. (Orlando Mack), 1824-1899.
Sept. 30, 1878, Oct. 1 and 3, 1878
Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.
Sept. 11, 1891-Nov. 2, 1906
Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.
Apr. 1, 1879, Sept. 25, 1898 and 1879-1898
Graveraet, Robert
1850-1858
Harvey, Charles Thompson, 1829-1912.
July 15, 1897; July 9, 1907
Lawton, Charles DeWitt, 1835-1909.
Mar. 6, 1901
McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.
Aug. 1, 1895-Feb. 20, 1901
MeMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Feb. 2, 1899
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-1949.
June 26, 1896-Feb. 26, 1901
Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.
Dec. 2, 1898, Dec. 22, 1898, Oct. 12 and 18, 1899, and June 23, 1898
Smith, Samuel William, 1852-1931.
May 14, 22, and 24, 1906
Thurber, Henry Thomas, 1853-1904.
July 5, 1893, Aug. 25, 1893, Aug. 29, 1893, Sept. 29, 1893, Nov. 27, 1893
Warner, Fred Maltby, 1865-1923.
Jan. 23, 1901
Winans, Edwin B, 1826-1894.
Dec. 2, 1891